Very well, next part, I'm just
going to read it to you. Good luck. He already
predicts that at dinner he will have a
journey
to ask for help.
So he's talking about
these others who are very powerful beings. They were
very
good in their past life, very
generous. They did
n't study weapons, they didn't understand
emptiness,
but
because they were so generous, they were
born as very
powerful beings with a lot of abundance and
wealth.
Then he talks about whether they come
from their own side, so they couldn't
change. And this is a very difficult idea that
we can delve into further.
And the question is, after we die,
or when we come into this world,
why can't we remember? Why don't we remember
where we came from?
And it's a great question.
If we could remember
where we were before,
if it were easy to remember
our past life, I think we would
all be good people. I think there wouldn't be
international tensions, and we could remember
our past life.
And I think that sometimes when we are
studying Buddhism, we don't
ask the obvious question,
which is why don't we remember our
past life? If I had a past life,
why don't I remember it? Why ca
n't I remember it?
Because it's
completely unknown to me. And I think
that if we are  Honestly,
I think if we're honest, many of
us can say, "
I have a feeling about where I was in
my past life." But if we're
really honest, I think we can say, "No, I don't know. I don't
clearly remember where I was."
Sometimes I have a
feeling, like, "I
definitely wasn't a cook in my
past life because my
cooking skills are so bad," and something like that.
But I don't really remember my
past life, and why is that?
And all this poetry here, all this story:
if you expect that you could remember, then you do
n't understand where you're coming from. If you think, "
I should be able to remember my
past life," then you don't understand where you're coming from.
Okay,
still, you have a feeling that there's a
me
who had the body in my past life and
who had the mind in my past life.
There's a Middle Way school that
says, "They believe that Michael
is the consciousness of my thoughts.
The person who hears my thoughts
is Michael,
and that feels right. It doesn't feel
good.
I'm listening. I
have a body,
but I'm not my finger. Gisela, it's not the
gazelle finger that has it. The
gazelle finger is why we call them the
gazelle finger. So  That Jung is the one
and has those fingers,
but he doesn't have those fingers,
so Gisela, therefore, must
be like the spirit of Gisela,
and that spirit moves from life to life.
So, this one, Michael,
he dies in this life, he leaves
this body.
We can see how the body is left
aside and rises to another place, and then
we have to bury or burn the body.
Some of us
feel
that there must be a real Chila
that continues.
He leaves, he leaves this body and goes
to another world. We do
n't know what happens to the mind, right? The
mind is invisible.
You can see evidence
of another person's mind in their eyes,
in how they smile.
[Music]
Frown.
You can see evidence that they have
a mind in their face and by what they
do and what they
say, but you can't see the
other person's mind.
But we feel like it continues. He
leaves his body aside.
Probably he goes to wash his
mind with him.
His body is here, but Gisela,
and maybe it's mixed with Gisela's mind.
He would probably go to another life, to
another world, and leave this body. And
then Gisela...  He would take another body
later, that's how we talk about
it, and that's how we think about
it, and he exists
within this body,
then the body ages,
and he gets out of that car and
moves into a new car and keeps driving.
We feel like that, and this is what
the first punchline on the Mac is talking about, and it's
saying that when we change
lives, it feels like we're changing
cars, like we're switching from
an old car to a new one
and moving on.
But what you're saying is, there's no
body that gets out of the
old car, and there's no body, no being that gets into the
new car. That's not
who you are. You're not that person. You
also leave your mind behind
when you get out of the
old car. You leave your body; we
can all see that.
But you also leave your mind, and you leave your weapon
and tail, and you leave your bad tail. It's
not like there's a Michael,
and Buddhism talks like that, but it's just because of
language problems. It's
not true that Michael
gets out of his old body and goes to the bardo
for seven weeks and forty-nine days
and then enters his new body. It's not like that.
That's not it.  That's right, if that were the case, then
someone could recharge. They
should remember
their life will pass. Wait, I'm going to go
pay for the soup again. I'll be right
back. James,
my mom gave me a nickname
30 years ago. She called me the one who
burned all the pots. He burned all
the pots at the monastery.
If the children are true, nowadays it's not that
Michael leaves his body
and goes somewhere. Listen,
this is what
this poem is about. New seeds open.
New seeds of that Michael open. I am not
a person
who changes cars, life
after life. It's not like that.
Now my seeds are opening
like a gazelle,
and the body of a gazelle, and the mind of a
gazelle.
Then those seeds run out,
and the body of a gazelle stops, and the
mind of a gazelle also stops.
And then new seeds open.
Ten minutes after dying,
new seeds open. There is no more gas. The fact
that there are months at that moment is
just more seeds. It is just more
seeds that open, and that is a
completely different person. Of
course, he cannot remember what he
was before.  Of course, he can't
complete it. They're completely
different seeds that are opening up. Of
course, he can't remember it.
It's simply a new body and a
new mind. It's
not like he got out of his
old body like an old car and into
a new body like a new car. It's not like that.
The seeds of the old gas-powered car,
the old candle-fueled mind, and the
seeds of the old girl in which the
old one was, are finished. Now new
seeds are going to open up,
and it's going to be with a completely
different person. And of course, he's not going to
remember anything at all because it's a
different person, a different mind. And I
know we don't usually talk about this like this,
but the purpose of this poem
here
[Music]
is very interesting,
and I like to tell my students
how long it takes
for that Michael to become a
dog. How long does it take? Is
it really true
that he washes himself into the bard, into the
spirit realm, for seven weeks?
Then, if you're lucky, he picks a
new car. No, no, it's not true.
The seeds are opening up
65 per second,
65 per second.
So how long does it take to
enter a new body and a new
mind and a new person? It
takes a
65  of a second
and I don't know why we feel safe
if I die it's
okay I have seven weeks to figure
it out people are going to pray for me
that they're going to pray for me it's
not that urgent I have 7
weeks
to choose good seeds for the
future isn't it like that your seeds are going to
open in a 60 and Tiago 60 nail of the
second don't take it doesn't take more than an hour
to become a dog it takes less
than a second to become a dog you don't
have to wait for what do you think the
dog's body is like isn't it like that
your whole mind
your whole body
can change into another kind of being
in a second
don't think there's I have seven weeks
to prepare don't worry Garcia I
have seven weeks to
find a good body is
n't it like that
the seeds you have when you die are
these are going to decide what you
become it's not your choice it's not
even your choice that you are you not even that's
your choice the
seeds you have in your mind when
you die are going to
dictate what you are going to become and
our choice you have no
power if you have good seeds
that kind is going to be very very very  Well, very
happy, and all the bad seeds you
have, something
negative is going to happen with that person, with that type.
If part of you came from your own side,
then you could say that it's going to
go to hell. We have to say prayers, he's
going to hear us,
maybe he can remember his good
seeds, isn't it? You already left, you leave
your body, you
leave the old car, and you also leave
the old driver, and then you
become a new car and a new
driver. It's not that the driver goes
from one car to another car.
[Music] We have to
continue the text a little,
otherwise there's a danger that we won't
finish it in 100 years.
He says, look,
these beings and super beings are so
powerful,
you have to try to imagine
that this is a possible future life.
You know, there's
this children's game, marbles, that
you play with, this
children's game, marbles.
These others
play with planets as if they were marbles.
Not only
Ironman,
when they have fun, they
control Mars, they can throw Mars. Yes, they
are very powerful,
but they also have this problem.
They believe that  The pen was made in
Japanese. They think that buying a
pen... they still think like that...
they have incredible seeds that are
opening up.
They have the power to play with planets. They
can throw planets like
baseballs. But they still don't understand why. They do
n't understand that they are all seeds
opening up from their past life.
And so
how can they start to feel attachment to
something? How do things begin?
And we can talk for a long time about
why something good starts in your
life or why something bad starts in your
life, but to put it briefly, you can't
pinpoint the moment this
pen became a pen. You can
say, "Hey, if the pen was made in
Japan, when it
came out of the factory on November 3, 2020, yes, but what
was the exact time when it became
a pen?"
And you can't find that moment. You can't
find the moment
this pen became a pen.
When they finished making the pen, it was
at 9:30
and 10 seconds. That's when it came out of the
factory. Yes, but is that when the
front part came out of the factory
or the back part, Gisela? It doesn't matter.
About 10 minutes after 9, it came out.
From the factory, like that, but actually,
this is a really difficult idea. There
must have been a part that came out of
the factory first. Maybe there's
a conveyor belt, and this part
came out of the factory first at the
front, and then at the back. There must be
a time difference. This
part of the pen came out
10 minutes after 9 and 14 milliseconds, and
this part of the pen came out 10 minutes
after 9, like 50 milliseconds.
But when did the middle part come out of
the factory?
Okay, it will really matter. It
must be 14 and a half milliseconds. But what about
the middle part? The front part, the
middle part, guys? Who
cares here? Listen, you can't tell me the exact
moment
the pen came out of the factory
because there are pieces of time
in that moment that are too short
for you to see. Try to understand: a
second. A
second has a beginning and an end. A
second in time—this time—this
time has
the beginning of time and the end of
time, and it lasts a certain amount of time. Time
begins, time ends,
but there should be smaller pieces
of time here, but your mind doesn't...  You
can see those smaller pieces of time. Let's
say I'm trying to bake a
cake today for my wife.
They say it's not healthy. I don't care.
When you're sick and someone makes you
a cake, you feel happy, right?
And that cake is going to have many parts. It's going to
have the top, the
middle, and
the bottom. Now
listen,
if the parts of the cake are
too small for you to see,
if you can't see the atoms of the cake,
then you can't see any part of the
cake.
If you can't see the pieces of the cake, you can't see the cake.
Gisela, I
know I can't see the atoms of cake, I
know.
But when you put many atoms of
cake together, you can see it. You can see it, do
n't you understand?
When you put many atoms of cake
together and you say, "Ah, look, now I can see," it's
not that small, but still, there must be
an atom here, and there must be an
atom there.
And using the corners of the atoms, if you ca
n't see the corners of the atoms,
the edges of the atoms, you can't see
the cake.
The point here is that the cake isn't
made of atoms. The cake comes from you.
Time doesn't come from you.  Time
comes to you, rebirth in another
body, in another mind, doesn't come to you, it
comes from you, it can't come to you.
The atoms in this feather can't come like that, you can't see them, they're
too small, you can't see them.
If something is too small to see and you put it all together, you couldn't even
see the edge because the edge would be an
atom. Here, this would be the edge
of the atom. If you can see into the corner of the
feather,
it proves that the feather comes from you and not
from the feather. It's very interesting
if you're
expecting that because you had a very good
life, good things will come out of it,
and after you die you'll get a nice
new car. This is a misconception. There are
no cars
and no drivers; it's just more things
coming out of your friends. Things are
coming out of your seeds. There's no one
watching what
comes out of your seeds.
You are what comes out of your seeds.
You're not watching
what comes out of your seeds;
you are what comes out of your seeds. The
observer also comes out of the seed. Okay, do
n't think you own your body, that
you own your house, that you have your
job.
Everyone is coming out of seeds. No one
owns your body or your
job. No one gets a new one.  A new body, a
new car, it's
very interesting. All the things in your
life, all the colors, all the sounds,
all the shapes come from your seeds,
and the person who is seeing them also
comes from your seeds, and there is no one else, no
one else who had the seeds, right? Let's
go to the next verse. Will
we protect which band? I will
also have this medium.
Endesa
story: there is a story
that these others
have beautiful children. They are
called Ride Humo, which
means the sons and daughters of the
gods.
And when the others, the people in the
temporary heavens, when they see
their sons or daughters,
they feel this intense attachment to them,
and they don't realize that the children
come from their own seeds. Okay, Sela,
someone had a child.
Veronica and my friend had twins
last week.
Also, they also
have a goat that also had two
children. We have human twins and a
baby goat too. And the woman was so
happy and sent us a picture. The two children
are drinking her milk. She has
two little children and she is
feeding them at the same time. She was so
happy. When
you have a child
and it feels
like the child came out of your womb and you
feel very happy.
You feel a great
[Music]
you feel a great happiness that
today I gave life to a being, to another being.
You feel a great attraction, a
very strong attraction. It makes you do things, but
in fact, he says here,
you're not seeing your children
correctly. You don't understand, you don't understand
where those children come from. These children
come from your seeds.
These children were born from your seeds,
and you created yourself,
and you created within the pregnancy,
and then you created the child that came out of
you,
and they are all your seeds.
If you truly understand where
your children come from, then
when you see them, you're going to want to be kind
to them all. If you understood
who truly created your children, it's the
good seeds in your mind.
[Music]
And sometimes when we have a family, I do
n't know why, but
some people
after having children become more
compassionate. I've seen it many times in
my life.
People who are selfish
become more compassionate after they
have children
and learn how to sacrifice their own
happiness for someone else's. When
I was in the diamond business, I
had to hire hundreds of people. I had to
interview them. I had to find them and
interview them.  Hire them, train
them for 19 years,
hundreds and hundreds of people,
and after some years I realized
that moms are great workers, they are
number one, they are the
number one workers. If you want a good
worker, pick a mom. They
know how to sacrifice, they know how to
stay late. They know how to
finish the job.
Dad leaves, Dad goes to sleep if
the baby is crying, but Mom will never
go to sleep. So I always used to
look for mothers because they already know
how to sacrifice.
So sometimes
when you see a person who has a
child, it makes them
even more compassionate. And
sometimes
in my observation, I've never had a
child,
when you have a child,
your worries, your afflictions
increase, it makes you more attached, it makes you angrier.
[Music]
You become more selfish, you only take care of your
children, but you don't take care of
other people's children.
You are very
prejudiced or just very impartial. I must
take care of my children, but I must not take
care of my neighbors' children, not in the
same way. What they
are talking about here is
the wrong understanding,
the wrong understanding of where
your children come from, and they are using, they are
talking about the  Other people's children
know how others have children.
Tradition says that
children sprout like that in their lap; they don't just
suddenly pop out of their body. There's a child there
in their lap. It
seems like a very easy way to have a
baby.
So the idea is,
Whitson,
when children come out of you, there are two
ways you
can understand it.
You can understand that this beautiful and
precious thing is coming out of the seeds
of sharing things with other people. And
after you have your child, you take
even more care in caring for
other people's children.
If you don't understand where children come from,
then the birth of a child can
be a disaster.
You protect your child and don't really
care about other people's children. If
you understand
that your child was born from seeds,
then you would understand
that you must care for everyone's children
equally. Okay, now
there's an interesting dynamic
with others.
Their whole life revolves around
competition,
and it's very similar
[Music]
to humans who are very rich.
People who are very rich. I heard the
radio
late at night when I came back from
work. It's a... it
drives the beautiful one. It takes me
about 45 minutes. I live in the countryside. I live on
top of a...  I live in the mountains
and I have a dirt road, and when
I drive at night it's a
very beautiful drive.
Sometimes I listen to the radio,
and I hear things from
other places, from other states. I
listen to the radio from
completely different places,
and then I hear these famous people,
actors. Yesterday I heard an interview,
and they even talk about other
actors in movies,
and then they say, "My competition."
And that's how these
beautiful, very handsome, very good-looking
men and women are thinking. I do
n't know why they don't have a
Kobe belly like me. They always look very
beautiful,
but the more beautiful you are physically,
and the more famous you are,
then the habit is that you get
jealous or competitive with
other beautiful beings, with other
beautiful people. It's like a curse. It's a
very, very
serious problem for successful people, for
rich people, for beautiful people.
They sometimes feel
intense competition.  Yes,
or intense jealousy between them.
Now they're talking about this.
Now the Panchen Lama says, "You know,
these people have beautiful lives,
these others,
but what defines their lives, the most
important part of their lives, is jealousy. It's
not enough to be the
number one actor, it's
not the same as winning movie awards. They're
constantly checking each other out: '
She's more beautiful, she's
younger, she's
stronger, she
has more fans, more people are
following them than me.'
This is talking about the
emotions of these others.
They have two big emotions. Number one,
when they have a child,
they feel this intense love for their child, okay?
And then when they see another, they
feel this intense jealousy and this
intense feeling of competition." The
Panchen Lama is saying, "Look, I
thought more about these others, about
these very beautiful
and very rich people.
Two things define their lives: Number one, they have
their own children and an intense
attachment to their children
and a beautiful love for their children,
but at the same time, they
feel intense jealousy
towards other famous or
beautiful people. It's strange
that these very successful people, these
very successful beings,
should have intense attachment and
love."  for their children
at the same time feel
intense jealousy of other successful people.
Punch in the hand is saying
you should be a good person.
You should call other people
the way you love your children. He's
not saying that. It's
very interesting what he's saying. Don't
forget, don't
forget that you are a struggle
between the devil and the angel.
This is a struggle between the devil and the
angel. The devil says,
admiration, Michael,
inside your mind,
two different thoughts. Number one,
great compassion and love for your
students. That's so beautiful. And then,
number two, intense jealousy of other
teachers, for example.
He's not saying that. He's not saying that.
It's the first punch in the hand. He's
saying that. He's not saying, look,
you have good thoughts and you have
bad thoughts, and please try to
have more good thoughts,
and please try not to have bad
thoughts. He's not saying that. He's
saying
no one is having those thoughts. He
's saying that no one has those
thoughts.
No one has the love for their children,
and no one feels jealous of their
competition. No one is there to have
those feelings.
That's the devil talking.
If the teacher gives more, he says,
please try to increase your
loving thoughts, and please try
to eliminate your thoughts
of  Competition. If a weapons teacher
is talking to you like this, they don't know what they're
talking about. Because
when I tell you, you should have more
beautiful thoughts, like the ones you have
for your child, or you shouldn't have
competitive thoughts, like the ones you
have for other people at your job,
when I say this, I'm talking
about you. But there is no such thing as a "you." There is
no such thing as a "me." If you
believe there is a "you"
that has loving thoughts for
your children, or if you believe there is a "me" that
has competitive thoughts,
then you've already lost the war. You've already
lost the war. I'll
say it again:
if you believe there is a "you" that has
loving thoughts, and if you believe there is a "
you"
that has competitive thoughts,
and if you believe that you should have more
loving thoughts and that this "you"
should have fewer
competitive thoughts, you've already lost the war. You
're already listening to the devil because there is no "
you." Nobody is having those
thoughts.
Why do we have this class
if there isn't a "me"
to improve myself?
And if there isn't a "me,"
what's going to get worse if I don't study?
So why do we have this class?  There is no
I, there is no you, there are only
seeds, there are
only seeds, okay? There is no you,
nobody got out of the old car and into the
new car, nobody loved their own children
and hated other people's success, there is
no you, it's
simply seeds opening, it's
simply seeds opening. Our gas, so if there is no
I, then
how can I be happy? Who
becomes a Buddha?
Nobody becomes a Buddha, the
seeds of Buddha open,
then you are him, and then you are a Buddha. Do you
understand? So don't worry
about me. I
am, I am, I am today in
someone else's micro background. By the way, it looks like I'm
chewing on aluminum foil. There is no
I having
happy thoughts, there is no I having
unhappy thoughts. You are your
happy thoughts, you are the seeds opening.
So don't worry about
Delio, just worry about the
seeds. When you see yourself
being loving to your children,
you are watching your own
loving seeds opening. When you
see yourself being competitive with
other people, you are
simply watching
the seeds of competition opening. That's all there is to it.
What am I supposed to do? I'm
trying to understand. You
're watching the seeds
open, and you have to focus on the
seeds. Don't focus on me. Don't
focus on me.
Just focus on the seeds. It's freezing. I
have trouble meditating. Yes, I
know. They're seeds opening.
You're watching seeds open.
Although there's one last thing, and then we're going to
take questions. Okay, team,
answer the story a couple of times, but don't
cheat. It teaches so many days of the year
that I've already forgotten what story I told.
This is my kitchen. You can see my
kitchen.
When I get up at night and go into
the kitchen to grab a snack,
my wife hears me. I
keep stepping in the water. There's always water on
the floor,
and every night, silently, I'm
going to step on the floor. The water is
very cold here too. It's winter,
but there's no snow,
and the water is very cold, and I feel
responsible. I
feel like I'm a good person. I
feel responsible. I'm going to clean up the
water, and I get on my knees and clean up the
water. Maybe the dishwasher
made some water. Maybe we spilled some
water.  I
cleaned the water on the floor for like
5 or 6 nights.
Every night I would bend down,
lean on the floor, and clean the water.
And suddenly, I don't know what happened, I
said, "I'm tired of cleaning the water.
Maybe there's
a pipe that's leaking. Maybe I
should fix the pipe.
It's so much work cleaning the
water every night. Maybe I should figure out
where it's coming from." That's what we're
learning here:
don't focus
on the result, focus on the seed. And I
talked to my friend Daniel Garcia, and
he came under the sink and
fixed the pipe. So what the
first stain on the ma is saying
here is,
just worry about your seeds. Don't
focus so much on the result.
Just take care of your seeds. Also,
when you feel intense love for your
children, when you
feel intense jealousy at
work, that also comes from your
seeds. So take care of those seeds and do
n't worry about the "me."
Don't think about gas and Marc from Semi,
hang up on Maicon.
Love comes from the seeds,
and jealousy
comes from the seeds
and the gadget.
Jealous Michael comes from the friends
and the gay one, and loving Mike comes from the
seeds, so he works on his seeds. He
works under the sink,
finds the pipe,
fixes the pipe. The pipe is his
seeds. The problem is
that the person working on
the seeds also comes from seeds.
The person working on the
seeds
also comes from seeds. Therefore, the more
seeds you have, the
better you are at working with
the seeds. Even worse seeds
make more seeds,
and nobody is in control. The seeds you
have now
will probably be similar tomorrow
because they are creating the person
working with their seeds. The seeds are creating themselves.
The same person
trying to fix the seeds is also creating them. And
if there's a problem with the seeds,
there's a problem with the one
fixing the seeds too.
Kayalar sounds like Sanz. It'll be like
a vicious cycle.
What you're saying seems like we can't
improve ourselves. It's difficult, but
not impossible, as long as
you understand that things
come from seeds. You have hope,
and if you forget that, then you have no
hope. Keep focusing on the
seeds. Keep focusing on the seeds.
If you have bad seeds, it's
because you come from bad seeds.
So how can I fix
myself? How can I improve myself? How can I
fix my bad seeds? If I come from
bad seeds, it seems impossible,
right? Because you can do small things. You are
lucky, we are lucky that
the seeds grow.
We are lucky that the seeds
double, grow, double, double. You can
do one small good thing today.
If you can do one small good thing
today, then there is hope
because those seeds double,
double, double. So today,
a practical step:
if you want to have a good rebirth,
simply the small good things.
That's all,
simply the small good things. I
'm making soup. It's not a very
good soup. I
'm not a very good cook,
really. It's not the best,
but small good deeds for
other people. And dedicate those new
seeds, and let's dedicate them all
to international tension, to
the solution, to
international attention. Let's do small, one
small good deed today. How to
make soup: I'm going
to tell you how the soup turned out,
and whether I burned it or not, but
do one small good deed.
Dedicate the seeds. The seed will
explode, the seed will expand, and that's
all.
Make small good seeds
and let them grow.  Our only
hope. Very good, Timothy. Do you have any
questions for me? Do
you have about 20 more minutes or something?
Very good. Very good.
Thank you for teaching us today.
Thank you for asking me
this question. Continue with what you
said about focusing on the
seed and not focusing on me.
A couple of questions have come up.
When are we
focused on me or what comes out of the
seeds? More questions are being
asked. Could you explain this a little
more so we can grasp or
understand why we are taught to focus on the
tenderness within us, but now you
are telling us not to focus on me
and to focus on the seeds, which seem to be
outside of
me. Good question.
In the lower schools,
Buddha said, "Be a good person.
Try to make good seeds, and then
when you die,
you will have a new body, a good
body, and you will be in a good place."
That is the first turning of the wheel of
dharma. That is how Wood taught
beginners. Please make good
seeds. You are going to die.
You want to have a good rebirth, so
please make good seeds.
Then you can take them like a
suitcase to your next life, and you can
open them there.
What the first Panchen  Lama is
trying to say here,
don't forget
that the person working with
the seeds also comes from seeds
at the same time.
So the person trying to
improve their seeds,
the person making the good
new seeds at that moment, is also
coming from seeds. You see, the
seed maker
also comes from seeds. If you understand
that, you have a chance.
But if you believe that there is a person who
makes the seeds, a
seed maker, who doesn't come from seeds at the
same time, you're going to have
problems. Enough with having problems. So
try to understand
that the seed maker
also comes from seeds. For example,
if the seed maker is in a
good mood today, then the
seed maker will produce good seeds
today. And if the seed maker
isn't in a good mood today, then the
seed maker won't produce
good seeds today. So you have to
understand
that the seed maker, the creation of the seeds,
also comes from
seeds. And we need to sow the
seeds
that will make us good
seed makers. The seed maker, the one who
makes the seeds, the
seed planter, also comes from
seeds.
So
we have to pay attention.
To sow the right seeds to
be a good seed sower, we need to
spend some time
thinking and reflecting
because I am happy, because I am happy
sowing seeds, because I understand
seeds, because I create seeds.
There are special seeds for creating within
seeds,
and that is the root of all seeds.
What the First Panchen Lama is
saying is:
take care of the seed sower. Think
about this: because today you were in the
mood to come to this class, because
you sowed seeds before. Take care
of those seeds, take care of those seeds, don't
lose those seeds. Which means
keep encouraging other people.
Whenever you see someone doing something
good,
tell them, "
Wow, that was amazing what you're
doing." All this about rejoicing
and coffee meditation
in other people—
these are the real seeds
to make you a good being, a
seed sower. So take care of your
seed sower seeds. What's the best
way?
Simply tell other people how
amazing they are, and do it all the time.
By the way, don't lie, don't make up
stories. "Are you so kind?" If the
person is a fool, don't tell them they are
a good person. That's not...  I
'm not saying that to help others. I'm saying if
you see something really good
that someone else is doing,
then tell them how amazing it is. It's kind of
selfish
if you don't tell other people how
amazing what they're
doing is. I saw how you spoke to that
difficult person. You're so amazing. I
saw how much patience you had. I just want to
say that telling you is beautiful. I
wish I could be that patient. And that's it. Those
seeds of encouraging and
motivating other people make you
a better seed-sower. It's
amazing.
So observe other people
and tell them how amazing their
seed-sowing is. Honestly, when they
're amazing, this makes us better
seed-sowers. That's what the
Panchen Lama is talking about. Where
we sow seeds,
I think the School of Only
Subtle
Guards just finished its first book.
Works with them. Just
finished its first book
in the School of Only Guards. I think it's
the biggest book from the School of
Only Guards that has ever been translated.
I think it's the best book I've ever
seen about the School of
Only Guards.
And it's out now. Well, looking
online,
the book is called The Golden Key.  If
you really want to understand the school,
then buy the book, and the color version,
and ask him for awards,
ask him for awards, ask him for awards,
ask him for awards, ask him to teach classes
about it. It's incredible.
I read a sentence
recently that blew my mind,
and it's
always right, and he said, "Look,
if you really understand the idea of ​​the
refrigerator where you store
your seeds,
if you really understand it, then you can practice so much,
then
tantra is successful, then you can
teach, then you can practice the
teachings, decrees, you can live with the
angels if you really understand this." And I'm just like,
wow, that's
incredible.
So I'm really going to encourage you to
study this book. A lot of people told me to
buy the ebook.
By the way, it's
instant gratification. It's so amazing. With the
ebook, you
just order it and it arrives in 30
seconds,
so you have no excuse about
it. You
don't have to wait for
the mail.
It's
unfortunate because in the US, if you wait for
the mail, it can take like two years
to receive the book. You can buy the
ebook, you can receive it in
less than a minute.
A lot of people told me, "O Gazelle."
This school of thought is very difficult.
Well, there are two things you can do.
Number one:
if a book isn't difficult, it means you already
understand it. So, in my opinion, there's
no reason why you should
buy the book.
If a book is easy for you,
then it's because you already understand those
things.
In my opinion, you
shouldn't buy the book. There's no
reason why you should buy the
book if you already understand something. So
why should you buy the book? In
my opinion,
and in the tradition of Son Capa, we should buy
the book we don't
understand.
We should buy the book we don't
understand
because then we can go
deeper. And those Mix Mods have been
working for five or six years, and each
of them
understands their own book in a very
beautiful way. I want to show you something, and I
can do it.
Let me see if I can find it.
Here I go.
This is what we're going to show this week
in Mix Mods' classes. You can't see it
if you can come to Mix Mods' class tonight.
These are Mix Mods' themes. I
'm giving you a
secret privatization. Don't tell me.
Here's where it all comes from. Here are the
original sutras from 2500 years ago.
Translating six of these,
here's the life force,
that's like 2000 years ago.
Then come the books of plain magic,
18 centuries ago.
Then comes the Shanghai school,
16,700 years ago.
Then comes Dar McCarthy and all the
schools of logic, like thinking,
that's 1500 years ago.
Then comes the school of great morality,
Binay, sometimes 1300 years ago.
Then comes the Tang Dynasty in China,
great translators who brought it, like
Jiang 66.
Then comes the Lower Middle Way school,
this is Esca L'Aquila,
great writers like him, and they
also loved meditation
and wrote the great books of
meditation. This was 1300 years ago.
They wrote the great books about
meditation. After that came the
High Middle Way school, this is
Chandra Kirti.
They really understand emptiness,
incredible, some amazing guys.
This is like 1300 years ago.
And then the script, How to Develop a
Good Heart,
and the nephew, like 1000 years ago.
Then came Wire,
The Glorious Days, like  600 years
is layered,
and then came the study of the
different schools
in two different ways, studying
all the schools together.
These are the great ideas of the
last 2500 years. Now I'm going to
show you something incredible. Are you ready? I
can see you're very
interested. I'll do it. I'll make it
smaller,
and here are the books we're
translating. On one side,
we're translating six sutras. There are
some that are already available;
you can buy them.
All types of karma, the
Lapis Lazuli Light Sutra,
commentary on the Diamond Cutter Sutra,
commentary on the
Heart Sutra. You can buy them now; they're
finished.
All the topics, all the great topics
of ancient times are being
covered by Mick Knox.
On the left side, and on the
right, you can see the mixed books,
and they cover all the great topics.
All the great topics in the last
2000 years have been being translated
by Mick Knox,
and there are 27 translations.
And if you don't get them, you must be crazy.
You're crazy.
So if you have time, this week
we're going to have 60 classes
about this idea. You me  You asked
about school only, it's not my
fault.
If you really want to understand how
seeds stay in your mind, come to the
Mix classes. There are 27
different books we're
translating that cover everything very well.
Team, let's ask one more question.
This is a combination question.
Different people asked
about their partner
no longer having love for their
family and wanting to abandon them, and another
person asked about them
no longer having compassion for
others and not being able to
truly feel that way. What
advice do you have? You have
two different but
similar situations. You see, people lose their
love and compassion for others.
I like the question; it's one of the
saddest things in the world. On
one hand, you're in a
relationship
[Music]
and it seems like the other person is
losing interest
or doesn't love you as much as they
used to, and it's very disturbing. It
feels like water is
running through your hands,
and you can feel it when it's
happening,
and it's very, very sad.
This person had
feelings,
and now it seems like those feelings are slipping away. On the
other hand,
sometimes I'm the one
losing those feelings. I
used to care a lot about these
people, my family, my partner,
or my work,
and now I don't feel that passion anymore. I do
n't feel love for them anymore.
Instead of love, I feel like I
should be good to them. This is
my family.  This is my partner,
this is the company that employed me for
many years. I no longer have passion for them; I
no longer feel this passion.
But I feel like I owe them something,
and both are
very negative feelings. And I owe
love to my family, but I don't feel it, and it's
uncomfortable.
Or
look at someone in my family or someone
at my company; they no longer seem to have as much
passion about us
or me as they used to. And both
feelings are the same, right? Till, you
said it's the wall; it feels the same.
Love is being lost; love is gone.
What can we do about it?
And again,
fortunately,
the first law of karma says that
small seeds expand
rapidly. So, the first law of
karma says
that seeds double every 24
hours. If you understand seeds—I mean, that's
incredible—
it's like a super fertilizer.
If you understand giving seeds,
then the good seeds
you sow are going to grow like crazy; they're going to
grow incredibly. If you're
seeing that love is being lost, it's
like water on the floor. Don't try to
dry the water on the floor; fix the
pipe;
fix the place where
the water is leaking.
And personally,
and I've had a long life, so  I've
seen how love is lost many
times; it doesn't work, I think.
And to tell someone, "Look, it
seems you don't have as much love anymore.
You can improve yourself. You have a
family, you have a partner,
we care about you. Please try to
be more loving," and I can tell you that does
n't work
because
how much love they have
comes from you.
So you simply
have to plant more seeds of love,
and that can be appreciation. So
think about the people
who are serving you.
Someone is growing oranges for
my orange juice,
someone planted coffee beans for
my coffee,
someone planted the watermelon. Even in the
winter, so
many people are taking care of me.
I should show them love
and even just gratitude.
I'm living in the
winter in Arizona; it's very cold
outside.
I'm in the mountains,
but someone
is sending me electricity. Thank you. I do
n't know where you are, but I
know that if I pay my bill, you send me
electricity, and I'm warm, or cold on a
cold day. Just try to show gratitude
for all the beautiful things in your life,
and that plants the seed so that
this love won't disappear.
Love is something very, very big—the love
of a couple, the love of...  Your family,
your own love for family,
the love of other people for you—
you can replant it. You can think of that
spark once more by showing gratitude
to others today. Thank you for
warming my house, thank you for the coffee beans,
thank you for the internet. Thank you, team, for
organizing these classes
and working like a maniac all day and every
night,
giving us all these opportunities.
Show gratitude to other people, and the
love will come back. And it's so exciting
when it works, when it comes back, because it's
coming from the seeds. Right? It's so, so
beautiful to know how to make
love come back from your heart or from
other people in your family. It's
incredible, it's so, so
incredible to be able to
relearn love from your own side. It's
like fixing a plumbing problem.
So more seeds of gratitude, more
seeds of gratitude, more seeds of
gratitude.
Okay, team,
we're off tomorrow,
and thank you again, Sting, for
organizing this, and thank you to all the
translators.
I know the team has a great team
supporting them, and thank you to everyone. I
know it's a great group of volunteers.
Thank you so much to everyone, and to the
translators, thank you so much. It's a
headache doing these kinds of
translations, I know, and I don't know how you do it,
but God bless you.